<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Dracula</title>
        <editor>Travis White</editor>
        <sponsor>Humanist Data Lab, UBC Okanagan</sponsor>
        <funder>Social Science and Humanities Council of Canada</funder>
        <principal>Constance Crompton</principal>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <availability>
          <licence>CC_BY_4.0</licence>
          <p>Published alongside xslts to demonstrate how to convert TEI into Cypher to populate a
            Neo4j graph database</p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>Dracula</title>
            <author><persName>Bram Stoker</persName></author>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Grosset &amp; Dunlap</publisher>
              <pubPlace>Garden City, New York</pubPlace>
              <date>1897</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
        <bibl>
          <idno type="gutenburg">345</idno>
          <ptr target="https://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/345"/>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div type="novel">
        <head>DRACULA</head>

        <div type="chapter" n="1">
          <head>CHAPTER I JONATHAN HARKER'S JOURNAL</head>
          <opener>(_Kept in shorthand._)</opener>

          <p n="1"> _<date when="--05-03" type="central">3 May</date>. <placeName
              corresp="geo.xml#BIS" type="central">Bistritz</placeName>._--Left <placeName
              corresp="geo.xml#MUN">Munich</placeName> at <time when="20:35:00">8:35 P. M.</time>,
            on <date when="--05-01">1st May</date>, arriving at <placeName corresp="geo.xml#VIE"
              >Vienna</placeName> early next morning; should have arrived at <time when="06:46:00"
              >6:46</time>, but train was an hour late. <placeName corresp="geo.xml#BUD"
              >Buda-Pesth</placeName> seems a wonderful place, from the glimpse which I got of it
            from the train and the little I could walk through the streets. I feared to go very far
            from the station, as we had arrived late and would start as near the correct time as
            possible. The impression I had was that we were leaving the West and entering the East;
            the most western of splendid bridges over the <geogName corresp="geo.xml#DAN"
              >Danube</geogName>, which is here of noble width and depth, took us among the
            traditions of Turkish rule.</p>

          <p n="2">We left in pretty good time, and came after nightfall to <placeName
              corresp="geo.xml#KLA">Klausenburgh</placeName>. Here I stopped for the night at the
              <placeName corresp="geo.xml#HROY">Hotel Royale</placeName>. I had for dinner, or
            rather supper, a chicken done up some way with red pepper, which was very good but
            thirsty. (_Mem._, get recipe for Mina.) I asked the waiter, and he said it was called
            "paprika hendl," and that, as it was a national dish, I should be able to get it
            anywhere along the <geogName corresp="geo.xml#CAR">Carpathians</geogName>. I found my
            smattering of German very useful here; indeed, I don't know how I should be able to get
            on without it.</p>

          <p n="3">Having had some time at my disposal when in <placeName corresp="geo.xml#LON"
              >London</placeName>, I had visited the <placeName corresp="geo.xml#BMUS">British
              Museum</placeName>, and made search among the books and maps in the library regarding
              <placeName corresp="geo.xml#TRA">Transylvania</placeName>; it had struck me that some
            foreknowledge of the country could hardly fail to have some importance in dealing with a
            nobleman of that country. I find that the district he named is in the extreme east of
            the country, just on the borders of three states, Transylvania, <placeName
              corresp="geo.xml#MOL">Moldavia</placeName> and <placeName corresp="geo.xml#BUK"
              >Bukovina</placeName>, in the midst of the <geogName corresp="geo.xml#CAR">Carpathian
              mountains</geogName>; one of the wildest and least known portions of <placeName
              corresp="geo.xml#EUR">Europe</placeName>. I was not able to light on any map or work
            giving the exact locality of the <placeName corresp="geo.xml#CDRA">Castle
              Dracula</placeName>, as there are no maps of this country as yet to compare with our
            own Ordnance Survey maps; but I found that <placeName corresp="geo.xml#BIS"
              >Bistritz</placeName>, the post town named by Count Dracula, is a fairly well-known
            place. I shall enter here some of my notes, as they may refresh my memory when I talk
            over my travels with Mina.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
